Welcome everyone to mental health
Monday. We are so happy that you are
here with us today again. We look
forward to this uh each and every week
when we are going live with all of you.
Please put in the chat where you are
viewing from. And if this is your first
time, please let us know. Uh because we
want to say a very special welcome to
you. And you know, I know last week we
had uh someone from Pakistan.
Um
I think that was our and maybe Canada,
but it's always fun. It's always fun to
see where you're viewing from. Dr.
White, good to see you and to have you
uh here and hosting with me as always.
It's a blessing.
>> Greetings.
>> Yes,
>> happy manic Monday.
>> Yes, manic Monday. It my Monday was very
full and you know, my Sunday was very
full. So, I literally was like, "Is this
Tuesday or Monday?" Because I felt
[laughter] like Monday. I mean, I feel
like Sunday was full.
>> Very deserted.
>> But, um, yeah, it was it was a a manic
Monday, but we're here now. And so, I'm
I'm happy that the day is almost over.
Almost over. Won't be complete until our
mental health Monday is over. We're
looking forward to the topic, which is
question and answer, but we expanded the
question and answer. We are going to be
answering
mental mental health questions in
general to the best of our ability which
the ones we are qualified for right well
Dr. wife's qualified for all of them
[laughter]
>> for the ones that [clears throat] I'm
qualified for.
>> Um, but we're and we're still taking
relationship and marriage if that's your
question. We'll definitely uh take a
stab at those again as well. Those are
always a lot of fun. All right,
California. Rob Green, good to see you
here. And you watch each week. Well,
thank you. We are happy that you watch
every week. It
>> Rob, where in California? Yeah. Where
>> it's like that's like saying Texas.
>> I know, right? Because we know that's
Dr. White's home base. Oh, yeah. That is
my state. And since I'm a little bit
since I was born there, Dr. White,
you're you're a
>> you're you're planted there for for many
years now, but it's still my state.
>> I'm gonna, you know, I'm gonna show some
respect.
>> Thank [laughter] you. Thank you. That's
my state.
So yes, please uh just let us know where
you're w viewing from and if you want to
start putting in questions, you can do
that as well.
>> Uh but we are just happy you are all
here with us uh this evening. Okay.
Okay. Santa Cruz. Okay.
>> Wow, that's beautiful. That's beautiful.
>> Yes, it is beautiful. We that's not far
from where we moved to moved from four
years ago. So very close to the the Bay
proper. Santa Cruz. Don't necessarily
call it the bay, but it's right above
the bay on the coast. And so that's a
great that's a beautiful area.
>> I grew up going to SoCal Camp Meeting,
so I'm very familiar with all of the
Santa Cruz uh spots. The best let me
tell you the best vegetarian restaurant
in Santa Cruz. It is called Dharmas. And
I'm sure Rob Green may know, but Dharmas
is like it is a beast of a vegan
restaurant. Like
>> I can't even tell you. It's just great.
Great food. Food food. Big portions. I
miss it. [laughter]
>> My um daughter is a total foodie. So
>> your daughter
>> Yes, she is.
>> She would love it. She would love it.
>> She would abs that sounds delicious. But
is that like Indian? Does that sounds
kind of East Indian?
>> No, it's it's called Dharmas, but it's
vegan. Everything is vegan. And so Okay.
>> It's uh they have all types of food uh
there that's vegan. So, they'll have uh
vegan enchiladas.
Uh this barbecue burger that I always
get is so amazing. Uh with like soy
curls. It's like a sloppy joe, but I
can't even explain it. The salads are
amazing. They make the their vegan. You
guys are going to make me go on and on
about this. These are not your
questions. [laughter] I literally You're
making me go on and on. The biggest
portions. But anyway, if you're in Santa
Cruz, you should go to that restaurant.
>> Absolutely.
>> They should pay me for that plug.
Seriously, like I feel like driving to
Santa Cruz.
>> I feel like driving it would probably
take you eight hours, maybe nine, maybe
more.
>> I thought it was Isn't it closer than
San Fran?
>> It only like an hour closer.
>> So then it' probably be about five
hours. San Fran is like six hours from
me.
>> Oh, I don't know why I thought it was
further. No, it's further. Dr. White,
>> you think so? [laughter]
Hey,
>> I'm sorry because it would take you I'm
really from the central coast, right? So
that San Los a Bispo area that that
would take you five hours and then it
would take you two and a half almost
three more hours to get to San Francisco
depending on how you drive.
>> Interesting.
>> Yes. I'm telling you, I'm the I'm the
true Californian and I used to live in
San Diego, drive all the way up to the
Bay Area sometimes. I know that whole
coast [laughter]
and I know how long it takes. Okay,
guys. I know you didn't come to hear
about our vegan food and Oh, okay.
Okay. All right. So, okay, Rob, I've
Okay, you've you've seen us all. Okay.
At Campbell. Okay. Welcome. That was our
church. And yes, Brother Terry was there
and me and pastor. That's great. Well,
it's good to see you here on Mental
Health Monday. All right, guys. You can
put your questions in.
>> Oh, Rob Green, your daughter is in slow.
She lives in slow. That is where I mean
I've lived in St. Louis Abyispo and I
was born in Santa Maria. So that's my
real home. Wow. Bless.
>> Your real home is where were you born?
>> In Santa Maria.
>> Santa Maria
>> which is 30 minutes from San Los Abyspo.
I know people are like what are these
names? Where are these towns? But
>> lot of Santaas.
>> Lot of Santaas. Lot of Santaas.
California was Mexico. That's why.
>> There you go. [laughter] There you go.
>> That's why. But guys, we are taking your
mental health questions, not just giving
you a tour of California,
but we are taking your questions.
>> So, I think we got something from Enoch.
Enoch made this question. He's like, um,
[snorts]
>> I regularly listen to a sermon.
>> Oh, let's see. Let's see if I can put it
up. Let's see.
>> By Benjamin.
>> Is that where he's saying? Okay. Is this
what he's saying? Is this true high
city's example of Israel? He wants
>> this one about the Israelites. Is that
the question you're about to that you
want to answer? Because I can put it on
the screen.
>> Yeah. Enoch. Enoch is coming and I
regularly listen.
>> Uh so so there's a four question.
There's a question before that.
>> Oh, there's a question before that.
>> So it's a bigger it's almost like a
looks almost like a mini paragraph. I
regularly listen to
>> Oh, got it. Okay. All right. Here we go.
>> Yeah. I regularly listen to a sermon on
sermon by Benjamin
Nji SD Malaysia and he warns us to be
careful what we wish for because God may
give it to us whether for good or worse.
He cites examples from Bible. Okay.
>> You want the first crack or um
>> Oh, no. I mean, I'll take it.
>> No. No. I Well, I'll take it. Even
though it's not a mental health
question, I'll take it. Um,
so I don't think we have to be careful
what we ask for because God is going to
answer our prayers the way that he sees
fit. Even though if we don't know, even
though even though if we don't know how
to articulate them and what we're, you
know, or maybe the thing we're asking
for, if the thing is what we're asking
for is not good for us, he's not going
to answer that prayer. He's going to
answer it the way he wants to answer it.
So I don't think we have to be afraid.
We don't have I I'm curious to what
those examples are.
>> Yeah.
>> From the Bible because I can't
>> uh think of one where somebody prayed
something and then God was like, "Well,
you prayed the wrong thing, so here you
go." And you're gonna, you know, that's
[laughter]
>> I I'm sorry, Eno. I don't So, you would
have to maybe provide the example the
the the pastor or speaker gave you, but
even though this is not Bible Answers
Live, but we are I can't we're we're we
are Bible
We're students of scripture.
>> I attempt to be a Bible student, but Dr.
White's a Bible student and I'm married
to a a Bible student for sure.
>> No question about it. Well, um I think
first and foremost, we'll remember the
text. All things work together for good.
>> Amen.
>> To those who are called
um I guess according to his purpose.
Something to that effect. And I'm sorry
I can't quote the exact location, but
it's a pretty popular verse all the
same.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh the notion of God being
indiscriminate in granting our wishes,
it's honestly it sounds more reminiscent
of an accusation against Lucifer than
against God to be honest because it's
more like from a Luciferian standpoint
where he would give you whatever you
want or something like that.
>> Um God is okay. Let's let's put it like
this, right? Who's the better parent?
You or God? You know,
>> right?
>> God is obviously the better parent.
>> Absolutely.
>> Um if your child asks you for a pet
viper, right? [laughter]
Would you be like, "Okay, you asked for
it. Here you go."
>> Right?
>> And and and we are mere mortal. But we
would never do that to our child. Now
the question is is God does God have
more capacity for love than we do? Does
God have can is it even reasonable for
us to compare ourselves to God in terms
of love and empathy? So obviously then
if I ask for something and it's not
truly good for me, he's not going to
grant it. But here's what I would say.
Um there are lessons we need to learn in
our salvation journey. Okay? And
sometimes there are some things we may
request where God may see fit to say
this is going to help you in your
salvation journey. Um but I think we can
rest assured that God means means well
for us. Um and and I mean yeah so I'm
not trying to clown a minister who's
like be be careful. And the other piece
that I wanted to add to that is I think
the danger is when our requests are
totally focused on just what we want
>> rather than requesting something that is
connected to the grander scheme or what
you might even perceive as the grander
scheme. I think when we're requesting
something that is just completely
self-centered,
I think that's when we're more
vulnerable to quote unquote ask for the
wrong things.
>> And so that the warning I would take
from the statement from that minister is
as best as possible connect your
ambitions to the grand scheme.
>> Um because that's going to protect you
from making some of these uh requests
that would throw you off. And the other
thing, so now how do you connect to the
grand scheme? How do you even know what
the grand scheme is? Now that
underscores why we need to take the time
to be as connected to God as possible so
that we can be connected to his grand
scheme,
>> right?
Absolutely. Okay. Yes. I know someone uh
just tuned in and said, I was wondering
what the topic was. Well, the topic um
is we are taking your questions, but
we're taking your questions about all
mental health topics. We're not just
talking about marriage and relationships
and being single. We're taking those
questions too if you have if that's some
if that's the questions you have, but we
are talking are taking the questions
about any mental health topic that you
have and we will do our very best to to
answer them.
>> All right.
>> Um
>> so and if if we don't get any other
questions, I'll ask you a question.
>> Yeah, go ahead.
>> Related to um mental health. Okay. So,
it's a young couple.
>> It's a a young couple.
>> It's a young couple.
>> Okay.
>> You are you're in a restaurant.
>> Mhm.
>> Um and you're on one of your date
nights, right?
>> Mhm. and uh maybe maybe your your your
husband gets up to I don't know run to
the bathroom or something like that and
you know they they look over to you and
they're just like I so admire your
relationship. I so admire relationship.
>> Uh give us a tip. Give us a tip on how
we can experience what you're
experiencing 25 years in. What are your
thoughts? What would you What would you
tell that young couple?
>> 27 years in, but um
>> 27. And what did I say? Did I say 25?
>> You said 25. 27.
>> Yeah, I'm telling my I'm telling on
myself.
>> Yeah, yours are You guys are 25.
>> Yeah, we're we're young bucks.
>> Yes. Let me think. Okay. I a tip. What
have I learned the most? Um
there's so much, but of I mean, we
talked about this last week. I mean,
that's huge. And I had an opportunity to
um practice it this week [laughter] or
late last week, I should say, because we
talked about not going to sleep or not
letting the sun set on our wrath.
>> I got a chance to to practice that
[laughter]
and I literally was like, "Oh boy, I was
just thinking about talking about this."
But um but seriously, that is a huge
thing to to be able to learn how and
that just takes me back to how to
communicate. So, uh, learning how to
communicate with empathy and
understanding,
be
get gathering enough maturity to be able
to
let my husband know, okay, we we need to
continue to talk about this, but right
now, we both can't emotionally talk
about it. So, let's take a break and
then let's come back later and let's
deal with it before we go to bed before
before the day is completely over. Um,
that is what I Yes, I definitely would
say that that's probably one of the
biggest things because when you're able
to take a mature time out and put
yourself on timeout
um and and then come back and discuss it
later, it saves you a lot of yelling or
screaming or insulting and hurting each
other's feelings and saying things that
you're going to regret and all of that
because if you don't take that time out
to calm down and breathe, you're going
to deeply offend each other.
>> That's profound. That's very um
profound. Now, let me ask you this
question as a followup.
>> Okay.
>> What do you tend to do in the cooling
off period? What what what do you what
what do you tend to do to to cool
yourself down?
>> Yeah, that's a that's a good question.
Good followup. Um, so for me, I mean,
I'm I'm we the most of our viewers are
Christians and some may not be, but for
me, I'm going to take some time just
talking to God. just talking to God and
trying to figure some things out and
just let my heart rate go down so I can
open up this part of my brain that's
like [laughter] wise and think and and
really talk to myself and be like,
"Okay,
just letting the Holy Spirit minister to
me to calm me down and remind myself
not to take everything so personal. Try
to see things from other sides." You
know what I'm saying? It just takes it's
a whole bunch of dialogue that's going
on in my my head to remind myself of my
husband's personality. Now, this is me
as a therapist in 25 years in. I mean, I
surely didn't know this probably 10
years in, but just just knowing my
husband's personality type, mine. So,
cons considering that in the situation,
how is that impacting what we're
discussing and why we're so upset? So,
basically giving therapy to myself.
>> That's it. No, I think but I think a
powerful thing you said was you go from
talking to your husband to talking to
God. I think that's just amazing. I
mean, because there's so many people who
they pick up the phone and they start
talking to someone that's not
necessarily a good influence
>> or calling anybody. Well, calling
somebody or watching something that's
not helpful or sometimes just like
stewing in your own thoughts to make it
even worse. So, I think that was great.
Okay. Right.
>> Well, that was just to keep uselves busy
while you guys got your questions going.
>> And if we get if we get if we if we
don't stay busy, I'm going to ask you
some questions, too.
>> Hey, you know.
>> All right. We have, how do the pressures
of life affect our mental health? Great
question. and why some people seem to
deal with the pressure better than
others.
>> I'm gonna let you go. Um,
>> absolutely.
>> Kind of goes with your book a little
bit.
>> Exactly. Well, Deborah, um,
so what what's interesting is a lot of
people don't know that when we talk
about stress, there actually two forms
of stress.
Um, one form of stress is distress and
that's the stress we're often thinking
of. And but most of the time you hear a
person talk about stress, they're
talking about distress. There's another
form of stress. It's called ustress.
Ustress is actually good stress. Well,
what on earth is the difference? What
would be the difference between distress
versus ustress? Distress is what you
experience when the pressure and the
demand actually overwhelms
actually overwhelms your resources. When
your resources are overwhelmed, when
someone's asking you to do something and
you're exhausted, whether it's
physically, whether it's financially,
whether it's financial or you know your
energy or what have you. Well, then in
those situations
um then you actually will feel distress.
But there's another thing there's
another thing where a person is placing
demands on you but you have more than
enough resources to deal with it. That's
you stress. Well, your So now let's see.
You just said well um oh well she
[laughter]
moved the question. Uh so let me see. So
um so then you said and why do some
people seem to deal with life's
pressures better than others? Well
because they whether conscious or
subconscious have figures fig figured
out how to shift it over to ustress.
They know how to set the boundaries.
They know how to deploy their emotional
intelligence to shift things over to
where they can actually manage it.
Sometimes it's setting boundaries.
Sometimes they're like, "No, that's not
going to happen." Whether the no is
beautiful or ugly, but it's issued as a
no. No, I don't do that. You know, I
don't do that, so that's not happening.
Um, and so what they're doing is they
are employing the boundaries to keep
their life in the ustress zone where
they can deliver at their best. So what
does stress do to you? especially the
distress part, it'll shoot up things
like um cortisol for example.
>> And the body can really handle cortisol,
but when it pulses, when it's pulsatile,
right? So when you when you have acute
stress, right? Um you're scared of
something, you run, you hide, whatever,
you fight, flight, whatever. Um it can
accommodate pulsatile cortisol. But when
cortisol is chronically elevated in the
body, that's when it impacts the body
negatively. That's when it's neuron,
it's neuronally toxic. That's when it's
not as good for you. Um, so I could go
with a bunch of examples, but I think
you get the point. So, it's ustress
versus distress and having the emotional
intelligence to know how to keep things
in the ustress zone.
>> Yes. All right. Great question. Great
answer. Thank you for that question and
answer. All right. Um, I just got out of
a 13-year relationship with a
narcissist. He was abusive and turned my
mother against me.
>> Who also I suspect is a narcissist. She
deleted me from Facebook and Messenger.
First, I want to um I think it's
Michelle Walker. Um, I am so sorry uh
for your experience.
Um it's it's
>> you know I I don't um again know if that
official diagnosis is what he had or
even what your mother has but it's still
a the actions um are still um it's it's
very disheartening uh to have um and I
you know your mom you know turn what you
feel like was turned against you. Um, I
don't know if this is um, a question.
It's really just a situation. And so I
really am sorry and I'm sorry you went
through that and experienced that. Um, I
would definitely to being in a
relationship whether that was even if
he's not a narcissist but it was just
emotionally abusive um or if it was just
you know to be in it for that long
definitely think seeing a therapist in
your local area would be definitely um
not a bad idea because 13 years is a
long time
>> and um definitely want to encourage you
uh to do that and to you know hopefully
the relationship with your mom can be um
um you know even some family counseling
if your mother would be open to that. Um
I don't know I don't know the situation
but that would be that would be my my
encouragement um for your situation that
you are in but I'm sorry that you're
going through that because that's not
easy
>> at all.
Yeah, I'm going to leave that. I think
you answered that pretty thoroughly.
>> Okay. Uh let's see.
Um,
right. Okay, here's another question.
All right.
[sighs]
Thank you to me. Well, thank you. You're
welcome. What is the best way to love to
deal uh with a nosy older neighbor that
has no boundaries and shows up and
knocks on my door whenever to ask to
help with things?
>> Wow.
Dr. White.
>> There we have it. Okay. Um, well, thank
you. So, Oh, Denise. Denise, my friend.
>> Yes, Denise. Oh, our friend. Hi, Denise.
>> Exactly.
>> Denise. Um, you know, Denise is a
communication expert. So, [laughter]
>> she is she is
>> uh Yeah. So, let's see. Best way
in love to deal with a nosy older
neighbor that has no boundaries and
shows. Okay. Well, I think I think in
this kind of situation, Denise, you
would pause for a second and think in
terms of how you want to experience this
relationship.
Um, we all have
had our lives impacted positively by
folk who are older than us at some
point. Um, we've all had the sweet
little old ladies um, uh, that that were
kind and had nice words for you when
other people didn't have them. Um, so I
think deep down we all want to be kind,
generous, and, you know, just
demonstrate some reciprocity. I I think
we all pretty much do that. But Denise
is saying, well, there are limits. I can
already hear you talking, Denise. Um,
[laughter]
there are limits, right?
>> I hear her, too.
So the idea now being is I think in your
mind you have to get a picture of what
you want the relationship to look like.
>> All right. So the first step is just
identifying what you want it to look
like because then the next step will be
okay what will you communicate to that
person at which point in in my thinking
when they came over you would be
prepared to okay well we're going to
have a conversation since you're since
you're coming over. I gather this might
not be a person to invite for a cup of
tea, but it might be, hey, have a seat
outside here. You know, you might have
some two chairs set up or whatever. And
you just have a conversation with the
person. Um,
yeah. Hello. Tell me about yourself. And
you have a conversation. Get to know
them. See how they're feeling, where
they're at with things. Um, uh, because
sometimes people are
they're at the edge of their well-being.
They're at the edge. And sometimes these
might be gentle ways of crying for help.
So that's why I think finding out who
they are and what it is that you're
dealing with is so important, you know.
Um, and then after you've done your
preliminary assessment, find out who
they are, what they're about, why they
see you as their supposed solution. Um,
then you can let them know, hey, these
this is how I envision this
relationship.
uh these are the boundaries. This is
when it's okay for you to knock. These
are the things that I can provide
support for. And for those other things,
I would recommend you go somewhere else.
Um um but yeah, you you now have a
setting where you can frame how you want
things to unfold.
>> Yeah.
>> Um obviously I can't give you specific
advice to the situation because I don't
know the situation. I don't know if the
person's dangerous and you know I I
don't know those details but I just want
to say those are some of the general
principles is assess the sit well get
clear on what you want get clear on what
you need what you want and then you can
start strategizing on how you want to
communicate it and then you have the
conversation with the person understand
where they're coming from and then you
know how to then fit your demands into
that situation this is this is what I
would
I
>> I hope that was helpful to me.
>> Yeah, I think that was very good. She
said Oh, okay. She said she did that
even invited to dinner and did that and
had the boundary talk. So, I guess
sounds like she had the boundary talk
and they're still not um listening or
not honoring your boundaries.
>> So, it sound like that didn't work.
>> Yeah, that's unfortunate.
I
>> that she went further than I did. Like
she's like I took her out to to dinner.
Oh my goodness.
>> Yeah.
>> And you had the boundary. Well, and and
of course the boundary talk is not
complete without um boundary and
consequences.
>> True. [laughter]
>> So if you do X, then I'll have to do Y.
>> Absolutely. And then there's actually in
enforcing and again we're not advocating
for anything crazy like violence or
anything like that but just look these
are the
>> do that.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
All right. Well, there are other people
listening to her.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. All right. So now you have Jas.
>> Yeah. Is there a way to develop empathy
hurt someone greatly but for some reason
I don't feel much remorse at all? Are
some people incapable of changing how
they feel about empathy?
H well
>> it'd be nice to know a little bit more
details in terms of what you meant by
hurting someone.
>> Yeah. But I maybe Yeah. Yeah. Maybe give
a little bit more detail. But in general
um you know I say praise the Lord that
our brains are are neuroplastic. So, I
mean they they were there to change
neuroplasticity there to to change,
right? It's not just in a stiff hard
thing that cannot we're really not
hard-headed. Not really. Um maybe we do
some things um that we shouldn't do that
makes us our our behaviors hard
hard-headed, but no, we can learn how to
become more empathetic. And again,
I'm'll be honest. I'm going to put this
in the Christian realm because if
if you're not a Christian to learn and
you naturally don't have a lot of
empathy, I think it's it's it's pretty
difficult to um it's not impossible, but
it is more challenging, I believe, uh to
to learn how to be truly empathetic. Um
because you know you when you become a
Christian, you ask God to give you his
love and view people the way he views
them. Well, you're going to be dripping
of empathy once if once you experience
something like that. Um and so I think
that but let's just say you're not a
Christian and you're wanting to learn
how to become um more empathetic. Um you
definitely have to um work on some of
your issues that are holding you back. A
lot of times there could be unresolved
hurt and pain and trauma that you have
not healed from and that's why you just
really don't have a very empathetic
heart towards others. You're um you're
you you hold your emotions back because
you're afraid of getting hurt again. And
I mean there could be so many reasons
but um if you go through a healing
process you will not after the healing
process and it's a journey but once that
gets better you your walls to protect
your heart those are going to start to
come down and you can start caring for
others and um you know wanting to assist
others and just having a more loving
spirit towards others. Um so again
starting off with the first statement
our minds are not impossible to change
and new behaviors we can learn new
behaviors. So if you're not born or you
don't as an adult you just not feel like
you're very empathetic.
We can change you can change as humans.
Our minds can change.
>> I love that. I love that there are
literally like parts of the brain that
are associated with empathy. And so in
the event that sometimes maybe you had
injury to that part of your brain or
something like that, yeah, there are
scenarios where you could um have
a difficult um you could have difficulty
conjuring empathy. There's a
possibility.
>> Um fortunately, it's rare. And I love
what you said about neuroplasticity. I
think
once you know the brain is neuroplastic,
then you know that we're capable of
change. And the only thing hard about
our heads is the cranium.
>> Yeah.
>> But actually the the gray matter, the
white matter, that's actually very soft.
It's very pliable to transformation. So
not saying it's easy, but uh
>> Right.
>> Yeah. There's hope.
>> Yes. Yes. All right. We have another
question. Any ideas on finding purpose?
I've done mar I've Let's see. I've done
marriage, kids, and don't value things.
um as house, cars, etc. for motivation
as most people use use to motivate.
>> Rob, are you Christian? Just curious.
>> Uh yeah, it's Rob Green and he said he
was that's the one that said he saw us
at Campbell Church, I would say. So I
heard
Well, let me know if you identify as
Christian, Rob. All right. You gonna
take the first dab? [sighs]
>> I was going to let you. I took the first
stab at the last one.
>> Okay, no problem. Um, so at the
mastermind institute, um, we have a
branded approach to purpose and we talk
about there being three dimensions to
purpose. It's almost like those three
dimensions form a triangle and your
purpose lives within it. The first
dimension of purpose is
the defining moments from your your
path. Okay, that first dimension is your
path. And if we were to sit down, Rob,
I'm I'm pretty sure there are these
moments in your life, these things that
occur that actually define you and shape
who it is that you are today. So that
first dimension is your path. So in
other words, it's worth taking some
times at times to think what are some of
the key issues that have impacted my
life that help define who I am. The next
dimension of purpose is talent. We all
have a talent. We all have something
that we have a natural aptitude in. Um
well, we have a responsibility to
distill that talent into skill and that
is the second dimension of your purpose.
Because you can see um I am paraphrasing
but King Solomon says a man or woman
skilled in his craft will serve kings.
I'm paraphrasing that brutally
unfortunately but that it in other words
it opens doors it opens doors for you to
get skilled um but that contributes to
your purpose and then the third
dimension to your purpose is the calling
it is impact so in a secular sense we
talk about impact um in a Christian
religious context
it's a calling to be godlike
M
>> so um Rob, we are entrusted with
situations to show what God would look
like in that situation.
>> And so now when you line up those three
dimensions, you're going to see your
purpose kind of lives in that. So now
you see why your purpose is so unique
for everyone. Everyone has different
defining moments, different talents,
different skills and called to make a
different impact. But those three
dimensions help you identify what your
purpose is. Let me know if that was
helpful, Rob.
>> All right. Yes. And he said, Rob said,
"Yes, he is a Christian." So, I'm sure
that was And yeah, he said, "Amen." So,
that was helpful.
>> Okay. Beautiful.
>> That that was helpful. Um Okay. Well,
guys, we are taking your questions uh on
any mental health topic and um
relationship
mental health topic that you want to
ask. a psychiatrist and a licensed
marriage and family therapist, this is
your time. We have time for more
questions. Um, want you guys to know
that this is our last mental health
Monday for the year. We will be back in
January, but this is the last one for
2025.
So, definitely um take this opportunity
to ask us questions. We uh definitely
want to answer your questions. While we
are waiting for more questions, Dr.
You're white.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Since you're always asking me questions,
[laughter]
um
goodness. What do you find, um and what
do you find most challenging about being
a psychiatrist?
>> Oh man. Um that's that's easy. Um
[sighs and gasps]
it's [clears throat] it's interesting
the infrastructure that is supposed to
support you. And I mean it's like simple
things like insurance
>> and like insurance saying, "Hey, um,
>> we're not going to pay for that patient
or
um you know, hurry up." You know, it's
we're not sure there's still a clinical
uh indication for this or you know,
>> you're you're providing them notes and
documentation that you're needing like
so they know better than you. Okay,
>> you got to do that. you got to do that
or I mean, you know, and so I or just
denying like can you imagine you eat a
burger and
like imagine you own a burger shop and
you feed the patron, they paid for it.
Um, and then subsequently they're like,
I need my money back cuz I wasn't really
that hungry. [laughter]
But like imagine that attitude or a
middleman jumping, hey, you don't have
to worry about payment. I'll negotiate
payment. And they're like, well, since I
have a million, you know, patrons, um,
we're going to decide if you get paid or
not. And, you know, I just don't think
the person was that hungry. I don't
think the burger was that good. Uh,
yeah, you're not going to get paid.
>> And you're supposed to run a business on
that. That's unpleasant.
I would say that's
>> that is very it's very unpleasant and
that's um
>> that's I get the world of business here
in America. It's I I believe what the
Bible says the love of money is the root
of all evil. Meaning it's I feel like
they're they're interfering with
someone's care um possibly
because they don't want to continue to
pay out even though people pay into
insurance each and every month and when
they need it
>> they should be able to get the most out
of it. But
>> imagine everyone comes into the
restaurant the they order their burgers,
you know, and they all leave and 30 days
later you might get payment from I don't
know
>> that's
>> 80%. 30 days later. Like why? Like
>> why wouldn't you just it? Anyway, those
are some of the headaches that you're
just like
>> okay patients not appreciating the care
that's unpleasant as well, you know.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
when Yeah. Um there is a there is a real
issue of violence against healthcare
workers. Uh I mean like people wouldn't
even think about it but like here these
people you you've given your life to
service
>> and things will escalate at times to
where you know there's there's violence
and it's like
>> those are the things that just take
Yeah. They take the fun out of it I
would say.
>> Yes. Yes. Don't let my husband hear you
say that because he'll be like you're
not going [laughter]
meaning like meaning if he thinks that
there's a if I'm could possibly be in
danger. I've never had anything like
that. And I'm wondering if it's because
of the um
you know how you practice medicine or
psychi you know practice medicine the
way yours is set up that you run into
that because I've never run into that.
I've definitely r I've definitely been
cussed out
I've been cussed out I've definitely had
some fbombs once or twice in the last
eight years but
>> Right. So, and so that's just a
preamble. That's just a preamble of
where things can go.
>> Um, well, we're dealing with some we're
dealing with people who are are
demonstrating substance induced
psychosis,
>> right? Exactly.
>> Um, you're, you know, they're on 72-hour
holds. So, the whole hold concept is
you're a danger to yourself, you're a
danger to others, or you can't take care
of yourself right now.
>> So, you need to
>> um So, folks don't take too kindly to
that, you know. Um so you know so but
yeah we deal with some pretty high
stakes you know high pressure um
situations but
>> well at least you live in a state that
that that does that. Um
I was
>> well in Alabama there's no there's no
hold laws in Alabama.
>> You have to go in front of a judge and
say why you believe that this should
happen. By the time you do all of that,
the person could hurt themselves, hurt
somebody else. It is I know this is on
YouTube, but I don't care. This is the
most insane thing that I have ever seen.
I was shocked when I came. I was like,
what do you mean there's not a 5150 like
a you know, it has to be and it has to
be voluntary. Um they have to
voluntarily do that or you have to go
before a judge and it's all because oh
they're that's their constitutional
rights. You're stepping on them. Any
Yeah. And Yeah. Really? because people
don't exactly cooperate with this
process mind you. So you can imagine I
mean and and let me tell you like what's
interesting about it is you'll literally
have a patient who will say that so are
you having any thoughts of harming
yourself and they'll be like yes you're
like okay all right now I want to go
[laughter]
>> and you're wait a minute or they'll talk
about like harming someone else I'm
going to go and kill that person I'm
like hold on
>> and you have to take the time and go
before a judge who knows how I mean that
took a even if it took a Hey, it could
be it would be a day too long.
>> Well, does it mean at least your the
police force is a little bit more
responsive or can you even can you even
get the police involved?
>> You can, but they're just going to and
they will take them to if they get
involved uh and they they would just
take them to one of the local hospitals,
but they can voluntarily leave the
hospital once they get there. says,
"Man, that's uh
>> I don't want to get too political on
here because it's not about that, but we
can have a talk
>> mental health, but oh my." But anyway,
those are like
>> really Yes, we have questions. Here we
go, guys. How do you protect your heart
from a family member who is holding on
to I'm gonna get you a little bug thing
for Christmas because that's
>> Oh my goodness. It's like they're all
over me today.
>> I see that. [laughter]
Okay. How do you protect your heart from
a family member who is holding on to
anger, resentment, and bitterness? My
brother and I were so close. This almost
killed me last year. Uh mentally
exhausted. Oh, I am so sorry. I I can't
see the name, but to the but to the
person who asked the question
>> says Motti. Mi.
>> Okay. Is it okay? Amii is the name.
Well, Marty Xen Mi Xen.
>> Okay,
>> Monty, I you know, I am so sorry to hear
that. That that is very difficult. Um
when you're at just at odds with someone
you love um and um and they're just not
letting it go. There's really um
Okay, the first question said, "How do
you protect your heart from the family
member?" I mean, that's like setting
down boundaries. I mean, I don't know.
Like Dr. White said earlier, we really
don't have enough information on how I
we know he's holding on to anger and
resentment, but I'm in bitterness, but I
don't know how that, you know, showing
up. Like, is it um we just don't know if
it's just emotional abuse to you or just
being very cold and mean when they're in
your presence? Um I don't know. But um
>> you definitely um you can't do anything
about him as far as changing him. Again,
if you're a Christian, of course, the
number one thing that you are to do is
pray for him and yourself. But then also
if it's so hurtful and harmful to you
and you of course you're trying to
protect your heart is there needs to be
a healthy boundary of distance. Um
people even family is not allowed to
abuse you. you can lose uh the family
card, if you will. That doesn't give you
the right to treat people mean or be,
you know, also hold on to resentment,
but you can protect yourself from a
hurtful situation. Um, and you can love
somebody from a distance if they are Oh,
Mon'nique. Okay, Mon'nique, this is your
question. Um if they are if they're
harming you emotionally
um again if you're in their presence or
just of course physically not being kind
or verbally or whatever the case may be.
However you need to protect yourself,
you need to protect yourself and it
sounds like some distance is the best.
Um, and in that you could still be
loving a person from afar, but just not
putting yourself in a situation to be
harmed emotionally or physically. Uh so
and Mon'nique what I would and I
apologize for being distracted by the
fly. Uh but Mon'nique the one thing I
would offer is
when seeking reconciliation it can be
helpful to take some time to identify is
there any way is there anything I can
take responsibility for? Okay. Um what
can is there any of this that I can own?
Um, is there is is my side of the street
completely clean? You know, that's
that's those those are some things. And
then when you're able to identify, okay,
well, this is what I can take
responsibility for, sometimes that can
make room for some dialogue. And you can
imagine if there's nothing you can take
responsibility for that means
um it's going to be pretty hard to
strike up any conversation
because when when people are in conflict
um there are things people often have
time to hear. There are things people
often have time to hear. Um things like
here's where you're right or here's
where I'm wrong. people always have time
to be like, I got time to hear that. Um,
and what people on the other hand don't
have time to hear is how you're
perfectly right and they're perfectly
wrong. Like people that that those are
not conversations that tend to open up
uh dialogue. Um, and that's not to say
that you are in any way wrong in this. I
I because we don't know the scenario.
But I also love sister Tante that you
mentioned people can lose the family
card. You know, I think there are people
who when they don't think they can lose
that card, they don't own the reality
that you're responsible
to be familial.
>> If you want to say that we are family,
then that means you need to be familial.
That means there's a certain level of
respect you should show since we're
family. There's a certain level of love
you should show since we're family. Um
there's loyalty. There's all these
values, but you can't just say we're
family, but then act unfamiliar.
>> Um that that doesn't go. No, you can
cash in that card. You can act
>> and that's where you see the proverbs
saying there's a friend that sticks
closer to a brother. Um you there's a
there there's a there's a friend that is
more familial than a brother. So that's
a powerful statement that you said.
Oh, and then the other thing is do your
work. Like this is hurtful and this is
traumatic. So get yourself some support.
Find some therapeutic settings where you
get to explain what this means to you.
You can get it out there. You can talk
about it so that you can then identify
the behaviors that will heal you.
>> Um because obviously this sounds
hurtful. Um, so you need to identify the
behaviors that are going to heal you.
You need to identify the boundaries you
get to set to protect yourself as you
said. Um, and part of that reflection
hopefully you'd be like, "Hey, what can
I take responsibility for? How did I
contribute to this?" Um, or not. Anyway,
hope that was helpful, honey.
>> That was perfect. And hopefully that was
helpful to you. I thought those were
great answers. This is going to be Well,
we have time for one more after this
one. if you want to put it in the chat.
So, um, hurry up and you have a few
minutes to put it in the chat. But this
one, um, this next question is, "How
should you deal with someone who
complains about the same thing over and
over, uh, for years and then gets
offended when you share your opinion?"
Um, all right. So, how do you deal with
someone who uh complains over the same
thing? So, they just never um are
getting over anything and gets offended.
You know what? I would probably stop
sharing my opinion because there it's
just like a cycle at this point. Um and
I don't know the situation. I mean,
specifically,
uh, but if if if they keep complaining
and you keep sharing your opinion and
then they get upset with you, it's kind
of pointless. Um, and
it just sounds like um, you know, some
individual counseling possibly,
depending on what they're complaining
about, some family counseling. I mean,
there's a reason why um they do have
that spirit of complaining and just
never being satisfied and never being
able to to see things through somebody
else's lens. I mean, there's a lot
there. So, uh there's a reason why
they're doing that, but I think you're
probably just going to frustrate
yourself if you keep answering. I would
just be like smile at them and be like,
"Okay, well, uh I'll pray about that for
you." or I don't know, something where
you're not actually giving an opinion
because it's kind of pointless. Sounds
like it's pointless.
What are your thoughts, Dr. White?
>> Um, first of all, yeah. Uh,
well, since since we only have you,
that's why that's why we always want to
check and, you know, see, hey, am I
doing everything I can? And sometimes
when a person is saying something over
and over and over again, sometimes
they're wanting to be heard a certain
way that perhaps they're not
experiencing.
>> And so that's why they keep coming at it
again and again and again. Um, and
sometimes, let's let's say they were
traumatized or something like that. I
know it might not be that, but let's
just say that it is. There are people
who they're they've been traumatized and
you're feeling like, hey, can we get
over that now? You know, can we move on?
And they're not thinking that they want
to get over it. So, when people get the
experience that they've been heard the
way they want to be heard,
um, uninterrupted, you were present, you
were asking them questions. Um, and I
know Shen, you're probably like, um,
dude, I did all that. So, this might be
for the benefit of, you know, the
listening audience. Um, but when they
are heard the way they want to be heard,
that sometimes is what will have them
say, okay, I I feel at peace. And as as
a person who listens to people
professionally,
when people feel heard,
and sister Tanta, you tell me if you've
experienced this. When people feel hurt,
tell me if you've seen this before,
>> whether it's they are they they cry,
whether it's but they'll be like,
[sighs and gasps]
>> "Oh, yeah."
>> You'll see them take that breath of like
sad like [snorts] I got it out. like um
I call it an emotional bowel movement
like they
[sighs and gasps]
just like like and so that's what we
kind that's what good listening
facilitates. Good listening facilitates
an emotional movement.
>> Yeah.
>> Absolutely.
>> A lot of times we're leaving people
emotionally constipated. Okay.
>> Like we we're interrupting their
process. We we're asking the wrong
questions. we might, you know, talk over
them. And sometimes our
>> our body language communicates again,
[laughter] you know, you're saying this
again,
>> right?
>> Um, and it can feel pretty crushing when
you don't feel like you're being heard
the way you want to be heard.
>> Um, again, I'm not trying to say that
you're not doing a great job listening
or all that, but I just mean since you
asked a question, that would be my
feedback.
Yes. And I you said you asked if I've
ever experienced that. I experienced
that uh with with with clients the most
um using the the tool that I talked
about earlier or I've done on other
programs um with empathy and
understanding because when you're
listening with empathy and
understanding, you can't the the tools
are you can't interrupt. You're not
preparing uh your defense. you're really
listening like your ear [clears throat]
I tell the uh clients imagine your ear
to your spouse's or this person's heart
like you're trying to hear
>> their pain and all of these things and
so when I'm telling you a lot of times
when the couples do this you know who
just breaks down crying because they
have an emotional
movement if you will um are the husbands
because they for so long they just have
never really felt heard heard or and
they just they just break down when
their spouse and it goes on both sides,
but I do see it a lot with husbands when
their wife is just listening to their
pain and they're understanding where
they're coming from and they feel heard
and then they just let out the the
emotional side with the cries, but
they're they're happy. They're satisfied
cries of I'm so happy you finally
understand how I feel.
And I think the funny thing is like
people like kind of run over with tissue
and all this kind of stuff like look man
nobody ever died from letting the tears
flow or like whatever little snot but
like
>> but this process is so sacred.
>> Don't interrupt it. just let the person
be, you know.
>> Um, and it's not it's not uncaring, but
it's I'm way more interested in you
divulging what you need to divulge and
you getting it out than telling you I
need you to sanitize yourself for my
benefit. No, it's
>> absolutely
>> I'm I'm focused on you having the moment
you need to have.
>> Absolutely.
Well, all of our uh guest and viewing
audience, viewing audience, not really
guests, guys, your viewing audience, our
mental health Monday family.
This was our final episode for 2025.
We will be back in in January of 2026. I
don't have that date yet. We'll see. And
we have our third grandbaby that's
coming on January. Did I not tell you
that? January 12th. I I I said she. I
don't know if it's she or he. We're all
gonna be surprised. So, when the baby
comes. So,
>> guys, we see y'all in February. Okay. We
already [laughter]
>> You never know. Well, we'll see.
>> No, I can't I can't be in Austin
forever. We have to come home. Um but
even from Austin, we could do some
broadcast. So, we'll let we will let you
know when in January, but we will be
back in 2026 at the beginning [laughter]
of 2026.
>> Um, so definitely we want to wish you
all a merry Christmas and a happy new
year and just a time to enjoy family.
Um, and just re reconnect to the ones
that you love and hopefully just get
some some downtime. Um, so the holidays
are great for that. Even if you don't,
for some reason, if you don't celebrate
Christmas uh the way everybody does
traditionally, it's just a great time to
to spend with the ones that you love.
>> Absolutely. Merry Christmas, happy new
year,
>> and definitely remember the reason for
the season. Okay.
>> Most definitely. Okay. Well, have a good
evening and uh we'll see you next year.
>> Happy holidays to you as well, sis.
>> Yes, you too. Take care. Bye. Bye. Bye.
Bye.